Okay, moving to the next section, cellular injury.
Probably the easiest way to understand this section is to put it in the context of what we just covered.
So you'll recall that I said that a cell can be stressed, and that stress can lead to growth adaptations.
In particular, if there's an increase in stress, we would expect to see hyperplasia and hypertrophy.
If there was a decrease in stress, we would expect to see atrophy.
And if there is a change in stress, we would expect to see metoplasia.
Now, it is possible that the stress could be so severe that it exceeds the cell's ability to adapt.
Exceeds the cell's ability to adapt.
Now, why is that important?
Because if the stress exceeds the cell's ability to adapt, then rather than undergo a growth alteration or a growth adaptation,
the cell will actually become injured.
And that's really what this section is all about, cell injury.
Now, we could ask a simple question here.
What determines whether the cells of an organ are going to adapt or they're going to become injured?
Well, actually, there's three major factors.
The first is the type of stress.
So, for example, if a cell were to, or if an organ were to become inflamed,
it's much more likely that the inflammation would result in a growth adaptation than perhaps injury.
The severity of the stress is also important.
Just to give you a very simple example,
if you slowly cut the blood supply to the kidney,
the kidney will atrophy due to the decrease in nutrients.
So, maybe a classic example of that would be atherosclerosis of the renal artery
or fibromuscular dysplasia of the renal artery.
Either of these two pathologic processes would slowly cut the blood supply to the kidney.
And, as a result, the kidney would shrink in size because it would undergo atrophy.
So, that's slowly developing ischemia or a slow cutting off of the blood supply.
However, if there was a thrombus in the, let's say, for example, left heart,
and that thrombus was to lodge, was to break off and embolize and then lodge into the renal artery,
that could block the blood supply to such an extent that a cutoff of the blood supply to, let's say,
completely would actually result in infarction or death of the kidney parenchyma.
And so, here we see that sort of the same thing, the same theme in the sense that we cut the blood supply
in the renal artery, but a slow, progressive cutting blood supply of the renal artery
would result in atrophy of the kidney, whereas a rapid, complete cutting off of the blood supply
of the renal artery would result in infarction and injury of the cells.
So, that would be an example of the severity determining what happens in response to a stress.
And the third factor that determines what happens in response to a stress is the type of cell that is affected.
Now, what do we mean by that?
Well, one of the high-yield principles to be familiar with, and examiners like to go after this,
is the fact that neurons are very susceptible to hypoxia.
In fact, the neuron has the ability to withstand hypoxia for only three to five minutes,
whereas skeletal muscle, which is another type of cell, actually can withstand hypoxia for very long periods of time.
And so, the type of cell affected will also determine how the organ or the cell adapts to a particular stress.
Anyway, in this particular section, we're dealing with injury.
And so, if I just very quickly read to you what we have here on our text,
we say that injury occurs when the stress exceeds the cell's ability to adapt.
As I've already explained.
And the likelihood of injury is going to be based on the type of stress, the severity, and the type of cell that is affected.
All right.
So, moving on.
While we're on this topic of cellular injury, we should remind ourselves that as we go through the remainder of this text,
there are going to be many common causes of injury.
For example, inflammation is a common cause of injury.
You know, you can take any example.
If a patient gets an infection, a pneumonia, that's going to injure the lung.
At the same time, there are some chronic inflammatory states, like autoimmune diseases, that would also result in injury.
Nutritional excess or deficiency can result in injury.
We're all familiar with that.
In fact, much of the disease that we see in the Western world is actually due to nutritional excess.
And much of the disease that we see in areas where poverty is prevalent is really due to nutritional deficiency.
So, these are common causes of injury as well.
Hypoxia, very classic cause of injury.
You know, all of the myocardial infarctions and ischemic stroke to the brain are all examples of hypoxia.
And we're actually going to spend some time discussing hypoxia in more detail in a few minutes.
Trauma, common cause of injury.
For example, a gunshot wound to tissue will injure the cells.
And genetic mutations.
When there are mutations and proteins are not formed or not formed properly, that can also result in cellular injury.
Now, all of these themes are going to be repeated as we go through the text.
However, what I want to really focus on for the next few minutes is hypoxia.
Hypoxia is a nice model for studying cellular injury.
And so, we're going to focus on that over the next few minutes.
So, before we can begin our discussion of hypoxia, we really need to understand the term hypoxia.
So, let's do it this way.
Hypo means low.
And oxia refers to oxygen.
Oxygen.
And so, hypoxia is low oxygen.
And in particular, it's low oxygen delivery to tissues.
Now, recall that tissues are essentially dependent on oxygen.
And the reason they're dependent on oxygen is because oxygen is the final electron acceptor in the electron transport chain.
That accepting of electrons by oxygen allows for the generation of ATP.
And so, low oxygen is going to impair oxidative phosphorylation, leading to low ATP.
And low ATP, which is an essential energy source, will lead to injury.
So, why don't we just summarize it by saying low oxygen, low ATP, low ATP, cellular injury.
And that's why hypoxia causes cellular injury.
So, the next discussion would be, what are the causes of hypoxia?
And actually, there are three major, broadly speaking, there are three major causes of hypoxia.
The first is ischemia.
The second is hypoxemia.
And the third is a decreased O2 carrying capacity of the blood.
We'll actually elaborate on each of these in the next few slides.
So, let's start with ischemia.
Ischemia is decreased blood flow through an organ.
Probably the easiest way to think about this is, I'll draw you an image here.
This is the artery.
And it is feeding any organ.
It doesn't matter for this particular discussion.
And this is the vein, which is draining that organ.
Now, ischemia refers to decreased blood flow through that organ.
So, this is the way that blood would be flowing through the organ, obviously.
And ischemia can occur in two ways.
The first way, well, actually, there's three ways, but two very common ways.
The first way would be for there to be a block in the arterial flow into the organ.
So, if there's a block in the arterial flow, for example, atherosclerosis,
that would decrease the blood flow going through the organ,
which would then result in ischemia within this organ.
I think we're all very familiar with that.
It's a common principle in pathology.
It's going to result in many disease processes.
For example, when there's atherosclerosis of the coronary artery,
that results in angina, or episodic chest pain.
But we don't need to worry about those details yet.
We'll get those later.
The idea here is that decreased atherosclerosis of the artery
would result in decreased blood flow through that organ.
I think we all have that down.
The next, the other way by which we could get ischemia,
and perhaps this is something that we don't think about as much,
but shows up often on examinations,
is that we could decrease the flow through the vein.
And if we block this vein, for example,
then we would block the flow of blood across this bed.
And by blocking the flow of fresh blood across that bed,
we would decrease the amount of oxygen within this organ.
And that would then result in ischemia of the organ.
Now, there are many examples in pathology of this,
but there's one very high yield,
shows up on examinations all the time,
and that is a syndrome called Bud-Kiari syndrome.
Bud-Kiari syndrome we'll actually discuss in more detail
when we cover liver.
But in Bud-Kiari syndrome,
there's a thrombosis of the hepatic vein,
and by blocking the hepatic vein,
blood no longer can flow through the liver,
and that results in infarction within the liver parenchyma.
It can actually cause death.
That's Bud-Kiari syndrome, very high yield.
Another high yield derivative of Bud-Kiari syndrome,
as long as we're on that topic,
is that I can ask you the question,
what's the most common cause of Bud-Kiari syndrome?
So the answer in your mind should be
that the most common cause of Bud-Kiari syndrome
is polycythemia vera.
Recall that polycythemia vera is actually a disorder
in which patients have a high red blood cell count
due to overproduction of red blood cells,
and that makes the blood thick and viscous.
And the increased thickness and viscosity of the blood
leads to a complication of thrombosis or clotting.
And one place in which thrombosis can occur
is within the hepatic vein.
Which would then lead to Bud-Kiari syndrome.
Just as long as we're on the topic,
another classic example of Bud-Kiari syndrome
or cause of Bud-Kiari syndrome
would be a patient with lupus
who has something called lupus anticoagulant,
which creates a hypercoagulable state in that patient.
So anyway, I don't want to press too hard
on the specific examples,
but really at this point,
I'm trying to lay down a basic principle in your mind.
We'll really have a lot of time to talk about
the common and classic examples of Bud-Kiari
when we do the liver.
So this is one way by which ischemia can occur.
And of course, ischemia would be a cause of hypoxia,
hypoxia, which is the discussion that we're having.
A third way by which ischemia can occur is called shock.
Shock refers to a generalized decreased perfusion
of the vital organs.
And it can occur, for example,
if the heart's not functioning properly,
we get a cardiogenic shock.
If there's not good blood volume in the vascular space
because, let's say, there's a gunshot wound,
we'll have a hypovolemic shock.
There's also a neurogenic shock,
an anaphylactic shock, a septic shock.
In each of these cases, the central theme
is that there's a decreased ability
to perfuse the vital organs.
And of course, if blood is not flowing
to the vital organs,
that would be an example of ischemia,
and that would result in hypoxia of the cells
or decreased oxygen going to the cells.
The second cause of hypoxia is hypoxemia.
Now, hypo, we've got that same hypo
and then ox, oxygen, low oxygen,
but emia means in the blood.
And so hypoxemia refers to a low pressure of oxygen
or low partial pressure of oxygen within the blood.
Very specifically, it would be defined
as a p small a O2, less than 60 millimeters of mercury,
and that would translate usually to roughly
an SAO2 of less than 90%.
This sometimes confuses students,
the concept of hypoxemia.
And so I think that maybe we should take a step back
and review a little physiology here
in order to understand this concept a little better.
So why don't we do it in the following way?
Okay, let's remember that there's a certain partial,
there's a certain concentration of oxygen
present within the atmosphere,
which is called the FiO2.
This is really the fractional percentage of oxygen
within the atmosphere.
And the goal of the lungs is to bring that FiO2
into the alveolar air sacs
and to create something called the P big A O2.
So the P big A O2 is a partial pressure of oxygen
within the alveolar airspace.
Now that P A O2 squeezes oxygen,
that pressure is used to squeeze oxygen
across the interstitium and into the capillaries,
which then creates a P small a O2,
which is the partial pressure of oxygen
within the arterioles.
And then that P A O2, that P small a O2,
its goal is to squeeze oxygen
across the red blood cell membrane
to load oxygen onto hemoglobin,
creating an SaO2.
So this is sort of a sequence
of how oxygen is squeezed eventually into hemoglobin.
So the FiO2 results in a PaO2, big A O2,
which is the pressure of oxygen
within the alveolar airspace.
That squeezes oxygen across the barrier into the blood,
which creates a P small a O2 in the arterioles.
And then that squeezes oxygen
across the red blood cell membrane
into the red blood cells,
which then creates an SaO2.
Now hypoxemia, again, as I've already told you,
refers to a low PaO2.
So really, this number would be low.
But you can see that what actually feeds
the P small a O2 is the FiO2 and the P big A O2.
So any change prior to this in this sequence,
in the early phases of this sequence,
would also decrease the PaO2.
So let's just take some common examples.
If a patient is at high altitude,
all right, high altitude,
then when they're at high altitude,
the FiO2 is actually decreased.
Well, the partial pressure overall of oxygen in the air is decreased.
The overall pressure is decreased.
The atmospheric pressure is decreased.
And therefore, the oxygen pressure is decreased at high altitude.
So at high altitude,
the FiO2 would go down,
which would decrease the P big A O2,
which would decrease the P small a O2,
which would then result in a state called hypoxemia.
So that's one example.
Another example would be to decrease the P big A O2.
The classic way by which the P big A O2 decreases
is anything that increases the P big A CO2 would actually decrease the P A O2.
And that's because, recall that there's a certain pressure that can exist,
and it's a balance between oxygen, carbon dioxide, and nitrogen,
and nitrogen is a constant.
So any time the P big A CO2 goes up,
any time there's carbon dioxide building up in the lung,
the P A O2 will always go down.
You know, they're always opposite.
So what would be some examples where carbon dioxide would build up in the lung,
which would then knock down the P big A O2?
Hypoventilation,
where carbon dioxide gets a chance to pile up in the lung
because it's not being blown off.
That's one example.
Another example which would cause this would be COPD.
In COPD, you're very familiar with the fact that air gets trapped within the lung,
chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.
Air is being trapped within the lung.
And so that would also decrease the P big A O2.
Now, once the P big A O2 goes down,
then automatically the P small A O2 is also going to go down,
and that's obviously going to be hypoxemia.
Another way by which hypoxemia can occur,
remember that the P big A O2,
its goal is to squeeze blood into the capillaries of the alveolar air sac.
So let's say that we thickened the alveolar air sac
so that this pressure, the P big A O2,
would not be able to squeeze as much blood into the capillaries.
An example of that would be interstitial fibrosis of the lung.
When there's interstitial fibrosis of the lung,
the oxygen diffusion barrier increases or thickens,
and therefore oxygen can't be squeezed very well into the blood.
So that would be another example of how hypoxemia might occur.
So, again, I think if you understand the general idea here,
it gives you a very good grasp on what we mean by hypoxemia.
Now, obviously, any time the P small A O2 here goes down,
that's also going to decrease the SAO2
because this is the pressure that actually was creating the SAO2.
And you can review your oxygen dissociation curves,
and you'll see that to be true as well
if you were to correlate these numbers on the oxygen dissociation curve.
So I hope that clarifies the concept of hypoxemia.
But the general principle that I'm really trying to get at here,
aside from the physiology that I just mentioned,
is hypoxemia refers to a low partial pressure of oxygen within the blood,
and it's another cause of hypoxia,
which is, again, the broad topic that we're talking about.
A third way by which we could create hypoxia or by which hypoxia occurs
is to have a decreased O2 carrying capacity within the blood.
Now, in order to understand this,
remember that the dissolved oxygen within the blood
actually enters the red blood cell and then binds hemoglobin.
And it's hemoglobin that actually has the role of carrying oxygen to the tissues
and eventually unloading it at the level of the tissues.
Recall from physiology that the vast majority of the oxygen content of the blood
is actually due to oxygen-bound hemoglobin.
And so if you knock out the red blood cells
or if you knock out the ability of the red blood cell hemoglobin to carry oxygen,
that will also result in hypoxia within a tissue.
Let's just give you a few examples of that to highlight this idea.
And because it's one of the few places we'll get to discuss this principle,
one example of a decreased O2 carrying capacity of the blood would be anemia.
Remember that anemia refers to a decrease in the total red blood cell mass in the body.
And when there's a decrease in red blood cell mass,
there's going to be a decrease in the amount of oxygen being carried in the blood.
And therefore, if there's a decrease in the amount of oxygen being carried in the blood,
there's obviously going to be a decrease in the amount of oxygen going to the tissues, i.e. hypoxia.
And so one important thing to remember is that if we go back to our paradigm that we had just established,
and if you have an FiO2, and the FiO2 is generating a P big A O2,
and that's generating a P small A O2,
and that's eventually going to generate an SaO2,
what we should remember is that when we have anemia,
there's no problem with the atmospheric oxygen.
There's no problem with the ability to bring oxygen into the lung.
There's no problem with the ability to squeeze oxygen into the blood.
So the PaO2 is actually normal.
At the same time, the SaO2 is normal as well.
And the reason the SaO2 is normal is because the SaO2 just looks at
what percentage of the hemoglobin is bound by oxygen.
And so if you have, you know, if you've got, I don't know,
let's just pretend that I've got three red blood cells in my entire body,
and each red blood cell is carrying four molecules of oxygen.
In that case, I'm 100% bound because each cell has the ability to carry four,
and each cell is actually carrying four.
Now, if I get an anemia, let's say that I get an anemia,
and I knock out one-third of my red blood cells,
each of my remaining blood cells is still carrying four molecules of oxygen.
And so here I'm, again, 100% bound and 100% bound.
So the SaO2 does not, because it looks at the percentage of bound, of oxygen,
sorry, the percentage of oxygen molecules that are bound to hemoglobin,
it's not going to be altered in an anemia.
So I hope that's clear.
Another way by which we can have a decreased O2 carrying capacity of the blood
is carbon monoxide poisoning.
And this is a very high-yield topic for examinations.
And so let's briefly review this.
The idea here is that carbon monoxide is a very avid binder of hemoglobin.
It binds hemoglobin 100 times, with a 100 times affinity as opposed compared to oxygen.
Now, carbon monoxide is actually an odorless, colorless gas,
and it can sneak into the lungs, and then it can bind the hemoglobin.
And once it binds the hemoglobin, it doesn't let the hemoglobin go,
and therefore oxygen can't bind.
Now, in this particular case, the PaO2 will be normal.
Again, there's no problem with the FiO2.
There's no problem with the PaO2.
And there's no problem with the PaO2.
And so therefore, the PaO2 will not be changed.
It will be normal.
However, the SaO2 will be decreased.
And the idea here is that if you've got a red blood cell,
and it normally has the ability to hold four hemoglobin molecules,
but let's say it can only hold two because of the fact that the other two spaces are bound by carbon monoxide,
that's going to be a reduction in the percentage of spaces that are bound by oxygen.
And so the SaO2 will actually be decreased.
Now, important to recognize for examination purposes and for clinical purposes,
the common exposures that lead to carbon monoxide poisoning include smoke from fires.
So any patient that happens to be, let's say, exposed to smoke from a house fire
or some fire of that nature can develop carbon monoxide poisoning.
Another important source of carbon monoxide poisoning would be exhaust from cars.
And this is the classic example of a patient who might try to commit suicide by carbon monoxide poisoning,
where they start their car and they shut the garage door,
and the carbon monoxide slowly builds up within that closed space.
And then a third way by which carbon monoxide poisoning can occur is via gas heaters.
And that's a relatively high-yield sort of clinical scenario that can show up on exams.
The classic finding in a patient with carbon monoxide poisoning
is the cherry-red appearance of the skin.
The reason the skin looks cherry-red is because the hemoglobin is so tightly bound
that it creates the, you know, reflects the red light
and allows, and creates this red appearance to the skin.
However, it's deceptive because the patient actually has,
is actually hypoxic because they aren't carrying oxygen to their tissues.
So although they look very red,
they're not getting good oxygen delivery to the tissues.
Now, another important point here, and it's kind of high-yield,
is when you look at most textbooks,
they'll actually list the various things that occur in stages
as carbon monoxide poisoning occurs.
For example, the earliest change is headache,
and then the patients can get confusion, etc.,
until eventually it leads to coma and death.
Now, the leading of carbon monoxide poisoning to coma and death
shouldn't be difficult for you to remember because, as I told you,
it's a mechanism by which patients commit suicide
or an individual could commit suicide.
And so I don't think that's hard to remember.
But what is very important to remember,
especially for examination purposes,
is the fact that the early sign of exposure is headache.
And I guess this would also be important clinically
because if you've got a patient that has been exposed to a fire
or comes in after some type of exposure and you want to screen,
just a very quick clinical or clinical history screen,
you can ask the patient, do you have a headache?
Or if the patient complains of a headache,
you really want to then sort of raise carbon monoxide,
the worry for carbon monoxide poisoning,
especially with an exposure.
So for examination purposes, I would say,
very important to remember that an early sign of exposure is headache.
The third way by which we could decrease the O2-carrying capacity of the blood
is called methemoglobinemia.
The idea here goes back to a little bit of biochemistry.
So this is why it becomes high yield.
Again, examiners love to take biochemical principles
and when they apply to clinical scenarios, it's a great way to test.
So these things become very high yield.
You don't really see methemoglobinemia very commonly,
except on examinations.
So the idea here is that, remember that the heme in hemoglobin
actually contains iron.
And that iron is normally in an Fe2-plus state.
Now the Fe2-plus is what binds O2.
And I usually tell my students that this is very easy to remember.
Fe2 binds O2.
So if the Fe becomes oxidized and goes into a 3-plus state,
then Fe3-plus is not able to bind O2.
So if the iron in the hemoglobin becomes Fe3-plus,
that is called methemoglobinemia,
and the hemoglobin is no longer able to appropriately carry oxygen.
Now in this particular case, the PaO2 would be normal.
And we've already covered this.
There's no change in the FiO2.
There is no change in the PbAO2.
The lung is able to fill and gather oxygen
and blow off carbon dioxide appropriately.
And so therefore the PaO2 in the blood,
the partial pressure of oxygen within the blood,
would be normal.
The SaO2, however, is decreased
because if you've got a red blood cell,
then the red blood cell, again, is only able to carry,
for example, two molecules of oxygen instead of the normal four.
That would be a, you know, a 50% saturation.
And so the SaO2 would be decreased.
Now the next point to be aware of in this context is
when and what clinical context would we actually see hemoglobinemia?
And classically, it's seen with oxidant stresses.
Oxidant stresses would actually have the ability to oxidize the iron.
So what are some oxidant stresses?
Well, sulfa drugs are oxidant stresses.
Nitrate drugs are oxidant stresses.
Those are the classic ones,
and those are the way by which they tie in
a little bit of pharmacology on examinations.
Another group of patients that can actually develop
methemoglobinemia are newborns.
Now, in order to understand that,
you should probably go back and remind yourselves
that we're always oxidizing iron within hemoglobin,
and all of us within our blood
probably have a very tiny percentage of methemoglobin
floating around in the blood.
And that's because the blood carries oxygen,
and there's an oxidizing stress that,
there's an oxidant stress that's constantly present within blood.
And so physiologically, we actually have enzymes
that participate in creating the mediators necessary
to reduce oxygen back to its 2-plus state.
Sorry, reduce iron back to its 2-plus state.
Now, newborns, their machinery to be able to do this
is a little bit immature.
And so newborns are particularly susceptible
to the development of methemoglobinemia.
The classic clinical finding in methemoglobinemia
is chocolate-colored blood, chocolate-colored blood.
And the patients will be cyanotic.
So they often, you know, sort of the buzz phrases are
cyanosis with chocolate-colored blood.
Sorry, chocolate-colored blood.
Now, the treatment is IV-methylene blue,
and what does IV-methylene blue do?
It's important for being able to generate
the necessary mediators that will reduce iron back
to its 2-plus state.
And I've stated that here by saying
that it helps reduce iron back to its 2-plus state.
So if I were to say methemoglobinemia,
if I wanted to summarize methemoglobinemia
in just a very simple principle,
I would say just remember Fe2 binds O2.
And that's going to make it very easy to remember.
Okay, now we get to the general theme
of what are the consequences of hypoxia.
So we talked about three different ways
by which hypoxia can occur.
For example, we talked about ischemia causing hypoxia.
We talked about hypoxemia resulting in hypoxia.
And then we talked about decreased O2 carrying capacity
resulting in hypoxia.
So when we have hypoxia or low oxygen delivery
to the tissues, what's the consequence?
That's sort of the next discussion.
And the key consequence is that
it impairs oxidative phosphorylation.
I've already told you prior,
and we can repeat this here,
oxygen is necessary as the final electron acceptor
in the electron transport chain.
And low oxygen will result in low ability to generate ATP.
And low ability to generate ATP will result in cell injury
because ATP is a necessary energy source for cells.
So the key principle here is that hypoxia
impairs oxidative phosphorylation, which decreases ATP.
Now, what's the problem with having a low ATP?
And why does that cause cellular injury?
It's particularly when it's severe.
Well, the idea here is that ATP is necessary
for key cellular functions.
And perhaps the most important and highest yield
would be the notion that ATP is necessary
for the sodium-potassium pump.
Now, let's go back and remind ourselves
that cells have a sodium-potassium pump,
and the goal of that pump
is to push sodium outside of the cell.
If the pump fails, in particular here,
due to a lack of ATP,
then sodium will build up within the cell.
And if sodium builds up within the cell,
guess who's going to follow?
Yes, water.
Water will follow,
and when water follows,
the cell will actually swell.
And the swelling of the cell
can result in damage,
is a sign of damage to the cell.
So this is one important function
that gets disrupted.
And I would say it's one of the very important functions,
as you'll see in a moment
when we discuss the next slide.
The second function that gets disrupted
is the calcium pump.
Now, let me just tell you
one general principle about calcium in the cell,
and that is the goal of the cell
is to maintain a super low concentration
of calcium within the cytosol.
Calcium in the cytosol is very, very low.
Calcium can get pushed out into the blood.
It can get hidden in the mitochondria.
It can get hidden in the endoplasmic reticulum.
But within the cytosol itself,
calcium concentration is kept very low,
and it's done using ATP,
using an ATP-dependent pump.
And so if there's low ATP,
that calcium pump,
the calcium pumps can fail,
and that would result in a high cytosolic calcium.
And the high cytosolic calcium is dangerous
because it can activate enzymes,
which you wouldn't necessarily want
to activate within the cell.
So calcium is an enzyme activator.
The third disruption that occurs with low ATP
is that we switch from aerobic glycolysis,
which is very good at producing ATP,
to anaerobic glycolysis,
which then results in the byproduct of,
number one, the poor production of ATP,
and number two, the production of lactic acid,
which lactic acid would lower the pH within the cell,
and the lowering of the pH would cause precipitation
of both DNA and proteins.
And so this would be another problem
that would arise when we have low ATP within the cell.
Now, the very initial phase of injury
that occurs when there's low ATP is reversible.
And so examiners like you to know
what are the various findings in reversible injury,
and what are the various findings
if we were to go a step further
and have irreversible injury.
Very, very high yield, often shows up on exam.
So let's take a moment to actually review this.
The initial phase of injury,
as I state here, is reversible.
And what I'd like you to know
is that if you had to summarize reversible injury
in two words,
you would summarize it as cellular swelling.
This is the hallmark of reversible injury.
Now, let's just understand that.
Again, if the sodium-potassium pump fails,
then sodium will build up within the cell,
and as sodium builds up within the cell,
fluid, or sorry, water is going to follow,
which is then going to result in swelling
of the actual cell.
Now, this would have consequences
for various parts of the cell.
For example, let's say that I have a cell
that looks like this,
which has these little processes
coming off the surface called microvilli.
Remember that microvilli are present,
for example, in the small bowel,
and present, for example,
in the proximal renal tubule.
And the purpose of these microvilli
is to increase the surface area of the cell
so that you could better absorb products.
For example, in the proximal renal tubule,
you want to absorb the things
that you want to bring back into the blood
from the filtrate of the glomerulus.
In the small bowel,
you want to be able to absorb all the food
that's being digested along the brush border
or the edge of the cells,
of the enterocytes of the small bowel.
So the idea here, again,
is that normally some cells in the body
have microvilli.
However, if these cells become hypoxic
and lose their oxygen
and then subsequently can't produce ATP,
sodium is going to build up in these cells.
And as sodium builds up,
water is going to come in.
And as water comes in,
these microvilli are going to be,
the cell is going to swell up
and these microvilli are going to be effaced
or lost so that the microvilli
are no longer present.
It's sort of like taking a hospital glove
or a medical examiner's glove
and blowing it up
and the fingers will disappear
as you put more air into the glove.
So as you put more water into the cell,
these fingers on the surface of the cell
are going to disappear.
So that's why one of the hallmarks
of reversible injury
is loss of microvilli.
So most textbooks will tell you
and examinations will ask you
about the loss of microvilli.
Another important feature
of reversible injury,
it again goes back to cellular swelling,
is membrane blubbing.
So let's go back and remind ourselves
that if this is the cell,
the cell contains something
called a cytoskeleton
and the cytoskeleton
maintains the size and shape of the cell
but also maintains the integrity
of the membrane
along the surface of the cell.
Now if there is excess water
coming into the cell,
then little blebs can form
on the surface of the membrane
as they sort of pull away
from the cytoskeleton
and that would be another sign
of reversible injury.
But again, what's the key principle?
Reversible cellular swelling.
So that's the hallmark.
That's why I say that
if you just understand cellular swelling,
everything else is sort of
a consequence of that.
All right, the third problem
that could arise in reversible injury
is swelling of the rough endoplasmic reticulum.
Now I mean if we've got a cell
and within that cell
we've sort of got this endoplasmic reticulum
and this is rough endoplasmic reticulum
with ribosomes sitting along the edge,
that organelle itself,
the endoplasmic reticulum
is going to fill up with water
and it will swell
and when it swells
that will also be a sign
of reversible injury.
Now let's go back
and just remind ourselves
the ribosomes that are attached
to the endoplasmic reticulum
are those attached covalently
or is it a loose association?
It's a loose association.
And so because it's a loose association,
one of the consequences
of swelling of the rough endoplasmic reticulum
is that these ribosomes
will actually pop off.
And so when these ribosomes pop off,
protein can no longer
be synthesized properly
and therefore another sign
of reversible injury
is decrease in protein synthesis.
So again, I don't think,
you know, again,
I don't like to memorize
long lists of things.
I think if you understand the principle
then you can really
put together the story
and that's the way
I would put together the story here.
The key hallmark of reversible injury
is cellular swelling.
That's the take-home.
Now, eventually,
if there's damage
and the damage persists
for a long period of time,
that damage,
or sorry,
if there's injury
and that injury persists
for a long period of time,
that damage will eventually
become irreversible.
Now, if I would tell you
that reversible injury
is summarized by cellular swelling,
then I would tell you
that irreversible injury
is summarized by something
called membrane damage.
That's the take-home.
The hallmark of irreversible injury
is membrane damage.
We could take this
one step further
and we will take it
because it does show up
on exams.
There are three membranes
of the cell in particular
that get damaged
and result in the key consequences
of irreversible damage.
The first is very obvious
and, in fact,
it's so obvious
that it makes for,
you know,
we use it sort of every day
and you'll see that
in a minute,
but it makes for
a nice exam question.
So let's just remind ourselves
that one important membrane
within the cell
is the plasma membrane,
which is the membrane
that sort of borders
the entire cell.
When there is irreversible damage,
this plasma membrane
will be damaged
and will be,
you know,
will be lost.
And as the plasma membrane
is lost,
that,
whatever is present
within the cell,
for example,
let's say there's an enzyme
present within the cell,
this enzyme will leak
out of the cell
and into the blood
and then will result in
that will be then a sign
of the membrane damage.
The reason I'm,
what I'm really trying
to get at here
and the reason I'm
pressing on this so hard
is think about it this way.
When you have a patient
that comes into the ER,
let's say you're
the ER physician
and the patient
comes into the ER,
if they're complaining
of chest pain
and you're worried
about a myocardial infarction,
one of the key
sort of gold standard tests,
you know,
the first test
would be an EKG,
that would really show
the changes,
you know,
particular changes
that would be important.
But another very important test
would be to simply
stick a needle
in the patient's vein
and take out some,
take blood
and then send it to the lab
and test for cardiac enzymes.
Now when you test
for cardiac enzymes
like troponin,
what are you really asking?
What's the question
that you're trying to answer
by testing for those enzymes?
You're asking,
you're asking the following,
you're asking,
was there irreversible damage?
Because myocardial infarction
means that you have
irreversibly killed off
the myocytes.
And so you're asking
the question,
have the cardiac enzymes
gone from the cell
into the blood?
And if they have gone
from the cell
into the blood,
for example,
troponin,
then you would say,
aha,
there is myocardial infarction
and myocardial infarction
is basically
irreversible damage.
So this becomes
a very high yield principle
because you test it
all the time.
When you're asking
the question,
you know,
if you're asking
the question,
does the patient
have hepatitis
and you're actually
measuring liver enzymes,
you're really asking
the question,
has membrane damage
occurred?
And i.e.,
if membrane damage
has occurred,
then there must be
irreversible damage
going on
within the liver.
So I hope
that makes sense.
Another problem
or another consequence
of loss
of the plasma membrane
is that the calcium,
which is present
outside of the cell,
you know,
so much effort
was made to keep
calcium outside of the cell,
as I mentioned earlier,
the calcium now
can rush in as well.
So the intracellular
calcium levels
will increase even further.
So these are the two
consequences
of plasma membrane damage.
Another membrane
that is going to be damaged
is the mitochondrial membrane.
Now, let's go back.
So this is going
to be a cell here
and we know
that within the cell
there is a mitochondria.
I can just draw it
like that.
This is pretend
that's a mitochondria.
And so within
the mitochondrial membrane
is important
because for two
very important,
for two reasons.
Let's remind ourselves
about one thing.
First of all,
let's ask a question
and it commonly
shows up on exams.
Where is the
electron transport chain?
The electron transport chain
is on the
inner mitochondrial membrane.
That's something
going to burn
in your brain.
Inner mitochondrial membrane.
And so if there is
membrane damage
to the
inner mitochondrial membrane,
that's going
to be permanent.
That's irreversible
because even if you were
to give the cells
oxygen,
to return oxygen
to the cells,
those cells would
never be able
to recover from
that damage.
So that's irreversible
damage.
It cannot be reversed
even if oxygen
is returned to the
tissue.
So that's one
consequence of
damaging the
mitochondrial membrane.
Another high yield
consequence of
damaging the
mitochondrial membrane
is that within
the mitochondria
there is a very
important molecule
called cytochrome C.
So cytochrome C.
Now, cytochrome C is
present within the
mitochondria and is
actually kept
very, it's
carefully guarded.
Why don't we put it
that way?
If cytochrome C leaks
out of the mitochondria
and comes into the
cytoplasm, it has the
ability to activate
apoptosis.
And apoptosis is a
mechanism of cell death.
So another consequence
of damaging of the
mitochondrial membrane
is that cytochrome C
can now leak out from
the mitochondria into
the cytosol.
And when it leaks out
into the cytosol, it
will activate apoptosis
causing cell death.
So that's another
consequence of
mitochondrial damage.
A third type of
membrane that is
damaged is the
lysosome.
Now, let's go back and
remind ourselves that
if this is a cell,
one of the organelles
within the cell is a
lysosome.
The lysosome is sort
of the recycling factory
of the cell.
It contains lytic enzymes
that have the ability
to trash molecules into
their basic building
blocks.
Now, imagine if the
enzymes present within
the lysosome actually
leak out into the
cytosol, those enzymes
are going to start
trashing the cell
itself.
It's going to
basically digest the
cell.
So that would be one
problem.
And that's only further
added to by the fact
that you know that
calcium has already come
into the cell and
calcium is an enzyme
activator.
So the presence of
calcium and lysosomal
enzymes within the
cytosol becomes a very,
very dangerous
circumstance, which
obviously would be
another consequence of
irreversible damage.
So again, these are the
high yields.
And, you know, I don't
memorize these things.
I'm really actually just
sitting here talking off
the top of my head.
I don't have any notes in
front of me.
And the reason I can talk
off the top of my head is
because it makes sense.
If you just remember,
membrane damage being the
source, being the key
hallmark of irreversible
injury.
Okay.
The end result of
irreversible injury is
cell death.
And cell death is a
separate topic.
We'll discuss that in more
detail in the next
section.
Why don't we stop here
and then we'll continue
on with cell death.
We'll see you next time.